thank you for joining me today on this
just impromptu call I wanted to connect
with you because you're kind of one of
my trusted sources right a lot of the
way you interpret information and are
able to kind of see the tea leaves
before everybody else does and it just
makes sense of it more appropriately
perhaps so I trust you as a resource as
a friend and I wanted to touch base with
you but I also figured you know if I
could record this and it would be useful
because I could share it with some of
the people in my community as well so
what we're living in interesting times
right mhm and unprecedented I heard you
say a word you know recently what you
called it a liminal event yeah why do
you think that this is you know as I
guess important as it is today
oh that's a hard question
hmm okay so let's start with maybe
almost in the beginning there's a if we
use the metaphor of the addict the you
know the addict
has a to be an ad means in many ways
fundamentally to choose to to
yourself and can choose to delude
yourself to choose instead of actually
perceiving reality to to keep have a
preferred delusion an explanation for
what's happening
that allows them to continue to be an
addict right that's the key the key to
the whole thing and you know within the
addict arc there's a downward spiral I
mean if you're deluded you're not making
good choices in the context of reality
because reality is trying to tell you
what's what to do and you're not
listening right yeah so you things get
worse so the delusion has to become more
intense and things get worse than
delusion has become more intense until
you hit rock bottom alright some event
occurs where reality hits you so hard
that your delusion pops loose for a
moment you have a moment of clarity a
liminal event are you entering through
space where the constructs that you have
imposed on yourself that have separated
you from effective choice making
suddenly drop and you're able to look
around and begin the process of climbing
back into sobriety now you may not make
it but at least you're the opportunity
to do that I think this parable is a
good parable for where we are as a
civilization right we are in a we were
deeply deeply addicted and we have been
deeply deeply separated from reality
along a lot of fronts right pick any
part of our civilization the way that we
are married
our dyadic relationships our families
the way that we educate and raise our
children the way that we produce and
distribute and eat food even the basic
stuff the way that we spend our time and
attention obviously the way that we we
choose our leaders and whether we make
choices as a community the way they ruin
our financial system these things are
all ultimately been running on
increasingly intense delusion for a long
time in our hyper fragile
and this is an opportunity really this
event it's hitting us is something that
is actually generating a liminal event
reality is hitting us we're actually
shuttling so think about how many people
right now in many cases for the first
time actually have to make meaningful
choices which is to say you know
whatever was I didn't know but my time
spans gotten very odd because things
were happening so fast but two weeks ago
probably for a lot of people the
question of hey should I go buy a little
like extra food and water came into
their mind right and their sense making
framework actually had to make a choice
do I just kind of keep going and doing
whatever I do or do I actually get out
of my normal habit maybe it's little
uncomfortable and go do this other thing
that possibly even seems weird and
wasteful yeah two weeks later you get to
you get to find out that the exam comes
back you get to see what kind of grade
your sense making framework had and
you're looking around going oh this
the store shelves are now bare I just
happened to have run out of of my
groceries because you know you consume
which you've got huh maybe that wasn't
the best choice like even just that like
people are now realizing that they have
to actually start making meaningful
choices I noticed my my teenage
daughters and by the way not just people
but also institutions so San Diego I've
got two kids in high school and on a day
let's call it eight days ago an email
goes out to parents everybody when
everybody's very concerned about the
coronavirus children just want to let
you know that under state law if you
pull your kid out of school they will
have an unexcused and excused absence
and so the bureaucracy the institution
with literally punishing parents for
making that choice okay fast-forward
five days and the school district says
schools cancelled until April 10th or
something like that and here's the best
part
and by the way Spring Break is now
canceled and pulled into that period so
we're basically getting rid of Spring
Break and we're kind of gluing it into
this event I think they're like the next
day they send that in to say apologize
apologize no Spring Break is gonna stay
and is still out so all right so schools
cancelled but now what do the parents do
yeah got kids that are no longer gonna
be a school what's the rule was to rule
in the house yeah
from from my daughter's the rule was in
fact what they're calling house arrests
which is to say sorry quarantine theirs
they've got their grandparents to live
with them so they need to be more
careful than most but then some actually
the numbers know him to be perfectly
frank but any event but only a fracture
their friends were equally under house
arrest
yeah day two a much larger fraction
their friends yeah under arrest
day three everybody everybody right and
so what's happening is that people are
actually just interacting with a
changing environment environment with
their habits aren't giving them good
answers they have to actually think
about the choices they're going to make
and those those choices have
consequences and those consequences land
and possibly land quite significantly so
that's one big piece yep
continue ok next big piece what is this
story about that's being addicts like
what happened what's going on here and
and one of the things that I think is is
kind of left hanging out and that we
haven't really built a capacity of in
our current civilization is the is the
recognition of the reality of something
that is known as complexity this notion
of what complexity really is and how
important it is in fact in many ways how
decisive it is and how we could possibly
go forward as humans and live in a
durable way and one of the
characteristics of complexity is this
notion of systems like complex systems
they're systems and they hang together
and very very subtle in interlocking
ways and they affect each other
so typically we and this is actually
pretty much everybody in the planet
right now except for indigenous people
have used what's called a complicated
approach to try to manage complex
systems and this is something I've been
harping on for a long time so I hope
it's not boring but a simple complicated
approach is like a silos you know in a
bureaucracy yeah I've got a you know an
academic gap ok at Department of
Mathematics and we got the Department of
Biology and I've just divided reality
into two distinctions
and there's advantages to that I can
specialize in mathematics and really
focus and learn a lot and go deep
analytically break it down to smaller
and smaller pieces but there's a
disadvantage to that which is that there
may be things about mathematics in
biology that actually are deeply related
to each other and I don't have the
connections between them that are
definitely part of reality reality
they're not separate then I'm missing
stuff that's it that's the academic
environment in our social environment
for example we have this notion that say
the physical experience of getting a
virus that the actual human embodied
experience of getting a virus getting
sick the institutional structure called
the medical system that is more that's
responsible for that the media system
that supports the way that we make sense
of our environment and the way they make
choices and let's go with listen the
financial system our distinct right
they're governed very differently the
Federal Reserve does not have
responsibility for for hospitals and
Kaiser Permanente doesn't that's been a
whole at a time specifically working out
what's going on MSNBC yeah well here we
are in a situation where they're all
complicated they're in a complex they're
implicated in each other and it's very
concrete we have a very specific you
know when the number of people who get
sick exceeds a certain number that is
the the logical as closely this is the
systemic assumption of our hospitals how
many ICU units how many doctors how many
Bentall errors have we economically
decided to put in place to support
sickness when a particular event of
sickness overwhelms that number then we
actually begin to see what's called a
phase transition in the medical system
it's no longer the medical system now is
this big broken thing that's still in
harm all over the place yep and remember
go sideways so it's not whether
necessary if you get sick from
coronavirus if you're in Seattle right
now and you get hit by a car you're
actually much worse off than you were
two weeks ago because the emergency room
is filled with other people
cascades out capacity is no longer there
and there's a called externalities the
externalities go up nonlinearly in a
phase drain
right so I've got some extra knowlet's
and I've got enough beds and I've got
enough doctors it's kind of like filling
up a cup with water as the cup gets
filled with water I could just fill a
cup of water I can just keep pouring
more sick people into it that's okay so
if I get a car wreck okay the the the
operator or the ER goes from not as
packed to more packed but it's kind of
okay but once I fill the cup with water
it's a totally different ballgame
now what happens is the sick person goes
from being less able to get access to
medical resources to possibly being
unable to and die all right well okay
that's fine so we just learned about
that so let's move to another one this
seems awfully less connected let's go
with the financial system well as it
turns out when people are and those two
implicate media in this as well when
people are getting a virus that's by the
way new and new is important because
novelty is a mystery yeah then for
example they start flying with their
choices change local people's choices
change because they have this notion
this sense that oh I could get sick and
as the media convey is a particular
narrative that influences their choices
well as we go fly less airlines make
less money and it's by the way just like
filling a cup again up to a certain
level it doesn't matter that much but it
passed a certain level the airlines
system subsystem begins to break right
they they have to just stop sending
airplanes and of course there's cascade
effects that people aren't traveling as
much then restaurants and events don't
have people who are in them and of
course the events might close down which
has a feedback loop in the opposite
direction then you've got the financial
system the stock market is watching all
of this stuff it's like huh what's going
on like in China you know did the event
occurred in China across all these
dimensions the Chinese airline stocks
went down before American airline stocks
went down but the people who invest in
airline stocks go well this thing
becomes a pandemic American Airlines
starts in German airline stocks are
gonna go down so they start selling yeah
and you get this a panic response at the
level of the financial system which is
not like you get a response like a
rational response if the economy is
gonna go gonna shrink so we need to not
be paying as much for this stock but
then as soon as the signal goes it goes
down yep and then just to be clear we
had a geopolitical consequence
we saw what happened oil prices and
whether or not that was a strategic
reaction like oh crap the economy
shrinking surger demand for oil is gonna
go down and we need to respond to it or
was an offensive move
hey this is chaos I should take
advantage of the strategic opportunity
and try to do something I come to grab
market share by flushing the price and
shutting that people who can't afford to
run at that price doesn't matter in
either case that creates a shock wave
effect in the financial system that
doesn't like big dislocation moves and
of course implications to cascade n2
uncertainty which then feeds back into
say the political system so that all
these things are connected and when
they're operating normally we get very
complacent and we kind of forget that we
have a deep deep responsibility that the
civilization that we live in is a rare
and precious thing and the fact that we
can tend to go about our day to day
lives
drinking $10 smoothies and not being
sick here in the West at the top of the
pyramid in particular is singular in
history has never happened before and
the baseline is it ain't the case and so
we take a look at those I personally
spend a lot of time let's take a look at
these various systems that are so
crucial in maintaining our our quality
of life and I can tell you they're not
in great shape
alright they're not in good shape
they've gotten very very very fragile
and this is part of that notion of the
delusion we've become an addict to a
particular lifestyle that is tries to
pit wealth against resilience and it
uses a
should see in the middle so efficiency
pulls resilience away and gives you
wealth gives you what's called plenitude
and that feels pretty cool for a while
right it's like taking a shot of them
feta means you can this massive burst of
energy but you're pulling resources from
the future into the present to get that
burst of energy you're pulling
resilience out of your biological system
in exchange for a burst of productivity
and by the way you can get addicted to
it so it's a good metaphor and so here
we are we're about to get a really
serious like oh you know moment of
clarity we're gonna we're gonna hit
reality is punching us in the face and
in the sort of medium article on this
recently like yesterday saying this is
the thing you need to be very clear that
the virus is a risk but it's one of like
nine risks that are now emerging and
there may be thirty risks tomorrow
because it's hard to see as different
systems move things that were perfectly
fine under ordinary circumstances
suddenly go outside of their tolerances
and they add more chaos and burden on
the rest of the overall system
you mentioned in that article yesterday
that you know things that the
institution current civilization the
structures the ideas the habits the
feedback loops that are hanging
everything together is in the process of
evaporation mmm-hmm and and then you
start talking about some of the
different Raptors like various areas
that basically could you were sort of
see it now like just start to crumble
maybe we can talk about a couple of
those right and go a little bit more in
detail if that's ok very concrete well
one of the obvious ones is the medical
system right yeah and you mentioned
already that you know let's say the beds
now if they're you know overworked
because they have more Cobin 19 people
coming in then somebody that gets an
accident is no longer able to get
support potentially right and at some
point will get saturated there
especially if the as the virus
propagates what other medical system
challenges do you see coming up
well they give you three no you actually
let me give you four and they're very
interesting related so one is doctors
and nurses getting sick all right we've
seen this happen all over the place and
as it turns out in spite one we have a
shortage of masks but the masks don't
seem to work very well
yeah nice so if a doctor is in theater
really surrounded by a lot of sick
people for a period of time and they're
not wearing a full-on hazmat suit they
will get sick and what that means is
that you know 10 to 12 10 to 14 days
later you're gonna have a start having
doctors and nurses dropping out of the
workforce you know so our actual
capacity of irreplaceable resources you
can't make doctors faster yep
starts to drop out that could be
catastrophic but it's a really really
big deal now I mentioned also Alice in
that essay that we can also think about
in terms of nested layers so let's say
for example in Seattle you get a real
issue like you run out of beds you run
in a ventilator as you run out of
whatever but see how this part of
Washington and if the rest of Washington
is okay the rest of Washington can kind
of like bring resources to bear but as
this as the pandemic expands more and
more places are implicated directly and
their ability to act as a backstop for
the rest for their age for their
neighbors goes down so it's a different
issue yeah okay let's go is a slightly
different one let's go to prisons
prisons are a really interesting and
challenging threat vector you can't
really do physical distancing some
prisons they're designed not to be good
at that I throw almost perfectly
designed to expose everybody you know so
you can get a lot of sick prisoners
that's a problem and and and they're
gonna just by themselves each prison
holds more people that can be handled by
it by an entire city's medical system
generally speaking but guards are also
going to be exposed yeah and if you get
sick guards or you get guards who
suddenly are like I'm not exposing my
family to this and don't go to work then
you actually said in the start having a
criminal or a prison fragility and we
saw this in Italy
my understanding is disciplic fifty
Italian prisons the last you know when I
looked at it we're essentially being run
by the prisoners
now that has its own kind of
implications in terms of just you the
human consequences on the prisoners in
the prison but you might imagine a
couple of those prisons suddenly stopped
being prisons and then they become
places where a whole bunch of people who
are infected spread and people who may
in fact go to great lengths to not be
quarantined yep and so you got a
dissemination vector that's implicated
that you can do the same thing with the
homeless right the homeless have been a
real real problem particularly in big
cities like LA and San Francisco and we
clear clearly are not good at dealing
with that problem is it's a it's a human
crisis and has been on the books for a
long time and growing and now it's
becoming a acute because again
quarantine is not going to work
particularly well on folks for just
living in tents in Skid Row in LA yep
and they're going to act as
simultaneously a reservoir of potential
infection for the rest of the population
and in particular check this out
so let's move to the fourth example of
the medical domain let's say that we do
in fact try to do something like a
chinese-style hard quarantine right
president comes on
being says martial law is declared the
National Guard has been brought out
everybody stay in your house yep okay
well the troops who are enforcing that
if they're not wearing hazmat suits are
now subject to being infected now as
young adults who are probably pretty
healthy more or less than us they're big
smokers they they're probably not
exposed to see like really serious risk
of death although the the consequences
of getting sick are seriously
non-trivial no matter what people you
need to make clear this is not the kind
of thing that you want to get but some
of them are you taking off out of the
awkward boards you may have some real
depletion of capacity chat your sort of
your your wall is trying to hold the
quarantine is gonna be leaking in
different places creating a stochastic
possibility of just events occurring
across that barrier and of course every
single one of those people they need
resources they need food they need water
they whip their families and they become
potential vectors to spread it and the
more you have them on the ground without
hazmat suits the more you're just
actually creating a breaking your own
quarantine all right yourself that's one
like there's like thousands of examples
in that subdomain let's shift over to
the financial domain I was just gonna
say that you know people are stopping
working now right yeah blood looking
from home well they're stopping working
and certain industries like airlines
hotels tourism all affected directly and
then multiple other industries are
affected indirectly and you know the
worry I think is you know first of all
if people are not working do they have
the means to pay their bills mortgages
and things of that sort as well as you
just does the economy come to a halt and
it seems like it is yeah let's run a
couple things and I can again like try
to try to think through the implications
of this across a bunch of different
numbers so something like 70% of the
American population there's paycheck to
paycheck and I'm not going to take that
as a humanitarian crisis I'm gonna take
that as an example of fragility I just
be like self let's just be selfish
that's fragility because what happens is
is that when something like this occurs
and when the economy does shut down
significantly
big sectors of it that tend to be
clustered with people who don't happen
to have a lot of job security like in
the restaurant industry you were going
to very quickly begin having households
that have income less than their costs
alpha times houses that have been kind
of zero and cash reserves of zero
yeah and in particular somebody just
sent me a message recently that we're
like looking at about six weeks of
having something on the order of 30
million men young men are 30 million
young men with no job no cash and no
family mmm well they may decide to do
things that are not that are antisocial
as they tend to when they're in that
circumstance and that's just a cascade
effect right so you start having
situations where people who literally
don't have resources either at the level
of suffering are you know gang kicked
out of their houses or unable to feed
themselves or having by the way
declining health because they have now
high stress malnutrition which makes
them increasingly large director to get
six across a bunch of different fronts
fYI you know historically that's why the
four horsemen include that plague
pestilence and famine are all part of
the same story because they feed back on
each other right you get people get sick
the crops aren't made people get hungry
they get more easier to get sick you get
a cycle okay let's do another one let's
go with supply chains all right we saw
this with China and this is this was
something that we were looking at a
while ago and then finally it became
mainstream but of course supply chains
go in all directions so now that Italy
is shut down and Europe's getting rid of
gets shut down the u.s. soon will be
shut down means that the whatever supply
chains we control whether we're at the
bottom of that but the supply chain
cascades back out to the rest of the
world which just means more cycle
dynamics and interruptions and slowing
things down even if people were going to
work there aren't going to have
component parts and then you've got
demand chain and this demand demand
chain going the opposite direction
obviously the u.s. is still the the
consumer of the world so to the degree
which US consumption goes down or goes
away in certain sectors I mean a friend
of mine does sophistic
financial stuff and he creates these
trading pairs and he did a trading pair
with jets which is airline stocks as an
ETF and then zoom conferencing it's like
basically long zoom conferencing short
air current airplanes yeah long net flix
short the NBA yeah but of course this F
cascade effects so people all over the
world are not going to be impacted by
crashing demand for things that they
produce in their environment and so the
and it's interesting I noticed that
they've been a lot of reports put out by
very sophisticated organizations like
Goldman Sachs they're sort of projecting
certain and complete IR consequences
they actually they're not good there's
their dire consequences but I'll put put
my my my neck on the chopping block and
say that a I believe there was a
projection and I by the way I could be I
can't remember we're calling it
incorrectly of a reduction of global GDP
growth to two percent yeah but it seems
really that seems very optimistic to me
very often I was just going to say if I
mean look right now we're probably at in
the very early days in the US right if
this takes conservatively three months
maybe more isn't that half our GDP in
the year that's gone and then how we
expecting I mean so that from if you're
even talking growth I think we're gonna
recede actually not probably growth
right well yeah and again remember we're
talking about fragility so if this was
like the the thriving American economy
in the mid-60s that's one thing this is
an American American economy that more
or less fell apart the seams in two
thousand eight is what how it was held
together with heroic in doses of
stimulants levels of methamphetamines
that would make a an addict shudder and
now is getting hammered again right so
things are already breaking let me
obviously the Federal Reserve's response
over the past couple of days is it was
called not measured I mean they'd they
dressed drop to zero but they obviously
had zero effect on the market to markets
like so what yeah you would that with
where else you got right they dropped
five trillion dollars in commitments to
the repo market
and you know that's out of control it's
absurd but it's an enormous amount and
so that's what's happening is is that
unfortunately addiction to stimulants
has that half-life you have to get more
to get the same hit exactly and now
we're running up now we're running into
into headwinds right we're not just sort
of sitting still we've got all kinds of
things coming at us and like I said you
know the geopolitical stuff is there
you know the geopolitical situation is
one where everybody's kind of waiting to
see like okay well how do i as my
position get better you know Russia
always is looking to play a chess game
that's China is always looking to play a
Go game right our current president
apparently likes to play poker but
everyone's trying to figure out how do
they get more chips or more what they
call dingo their little colored pieces
we're more territory on the board for
their team yeah and unfortunately crisis
breeds opportunity and in that context
all kinds of things are going on like
disinfo is increasing rapidly which
creates all kinds of decreases
probability know what's going on three
of strategic alliances are shifting I
mean it's it's a lot so so that's the
the sense making side of it it's
interesting right I mean even the
position of the US government I mean has
shifted so drastically in just weeks
yeah well why is it that the world is
having a hard time making sense of this
and and why is it that you're able to
make sense of it a lot faster a lot more
comprehensively than perhaps other
people what's the difference in sense
making that's happening well so what are
the things is clearly happening and it's
impacting everybody's velocity
things are happening fast and this is
that whole exponential curve right
people that I said like you know what is
it if humanity humanity's biggest
challenge right now is they don't get
the exponential curve something like I'm
missing the quote but we're experiencing
that yeah and so and I see it actually
oftentimes in just like on social media
you know there's only been one case why
does that matter how can that possibly
matter that's a thousand case it's how
could that possibly matter
and there's truly only people who have
have some facts like haven't had an
embodied experience with exponential
that had the ability to go yeah well
will thousand become
a million in two months yeah and a
million by the way becomes everybody one
month later like that's the thing I bet
you know that thought experiment I've
got a petri dish and I put exactly one
bacteria in the center of the petri dish
and the next the next day or the next
hour it doubles and it takes six weeks
to cover half the petri dish how much
longer does it take to cover the whole
petri dish yeah just few more days one
hour
no no one hour that's the thing right
it's doubling every hour that's true the
first six weeks is doubling from a small
base until it covers half but once it's
covered half the next doubling which is
exactly one hour it goes the whole so
it's like you jump out of an airplane
your body your brain is a use to moving
vertically at real velocity it's called
I think ground rush so you look down the
ground since for our way for our way for
our way far away you hit it that's like
a thing that they trained you with it's
like we're experiencing ground rush in
viral space because it just moves it a
rate that we don't make sense up and
then what's happening of course is that
the virtually nobody is trained in their
day-to-day lives to be dealing with
complexity so we've got velocity you've
got complexity going on simultaneously
so you just get surprised you know it's
like a you know measuring firefighters
where they're to focusing on the fire
they're focusing on the fire and then
suddenly gosh I don't even know what
movie they're I invented for like a a
plague of locusts just shows up out of
nowhere and starts like eating their
their hoses like we were going to do
with a local it's like what the hell
it's like that kind of thing now in my
case I have kind of three things that
have supported me the one is I started
out as an entrepreneur so at the startup
club like a startup tech entrepreneur so
things like pace like pace of change in
fact specifically exponential growth
where things that I learned hands-on
yeah and complexity like having to deal
with multiple different modal changes
like dealing with finance and legal and
technology and marketing and HR like all
these different things and having to be
able to state switch between them and
notice how they said back into each
other yep and I wasn't by the way
trained I didn't go to business school
or anything like that so I kind of
learned it on the streets as it were so
I kind of had
build competence to do it in general
here and then when I quit being an
entrepreneur I didn't just go hang out
at fancy Islands I joined the board of a
company called the Santa Fe Institute
which happens to be the pioneers in
complex system science so I got a chance
to say okay all that stuff that I
experienced firsthand let's talk about
the theory how does this theory work and
then about ten years ago I got very
concerned about the state of the systems
as I begin digging into each these
systems and asking very smart people who
are domain experts about say like you
know nuclear proliferation or
concentrations of heavy metals in very
specific biological niches they're like
wow yeah it's actually really bad and
getting worse fast like there's
fragility in the domain that I know
about and I notice is the two things
every single one of these experts that I
talked to was saying more or less the
same thing and if I asked them about
another domain that they weren't
familiar with they were sure there was
very surprised interested did you know
about this sort of it here they're like
no good I had no idea because you were
siloed we're stuck in vertical
disciplines and we don't cross
communicate so about 10 years ago I
basically just took it upon myself to
start trying to learn more about
precisely what these kinds of things are
about and had been thinking about
talking about trying to work to address
what's happening now so something's
anything special other than just kind of
sheer circumstance that I was prepared
for this event
you saw it coming you also knew that
this is one of those phase shift phase
transition type of moments and now let's
talk about what you see playing out and
we talked about some of the risks in
terms of you know medical financial
government so on what is a month later
look like to you like you know where do
you see the world going so we be
prepared for that we're not even
thinking about are considering right now
right so let me just kind of put it in
it first like a visual metaphor and then
say some scenarios so the visual
metaphor is let's say I have a marble
and I'm rolling it on like a glass table
but the glass table has a big groove in
it I
kind of very easily predict where the
marbles gonna go and it's gonna get into
that groove and it's gonna follow the
grooves down
I missed the groove steep enough it's
actually quite difficult to get the
marble to move anywhere but the groove
once it's in it it's stuck in it
okay what you see is the the the
language of science it means a
significant activation energy as
necessary to change the trajectory of
the system the system in this case is
just the marble and its trajectory is
that path but I imagined that what
happens is is that as the marbles
rolling down to the groove the groove
gets shallower and shallower so less
than less activation energy is necessary
to move it out of the groove and let's
imagine actually there's a certain point
where the group disappears completely
and it's on a perfectly smooth table
absolutely perfectly smooth and now you
can notice if you've ever experienced
anything like this before
it could go anywhere yeah it's
projectory now becomes almost completely
unpredictable your vacuum moved into a
chaos state all right
so well that is a visual metaphor what
we're looking at right now is some
scenarios our scenarios where the things
that are happening are kind of lowering
the the side to that that groove and so
the marble could get kicked out of it so
this is a phase transition each each one
of these subsystems is its own its own
groove so the medical groove once
medical overwhelm happens it gets the
marble gets kicked out of that groove
and with a different level of energy
there's more uncertainty in the system
yeah now there's one big scenario where
the powers that be and the kind of the
are capacities is people to come
together and do stuff hold together
under all of this and after some period
of time we're on the other side of
something that we can all remember and
talk about and so structural changes
have happened but more or less we're
still in the groove sure somewhat like
the 2008 yeah yeah yeah some people lost
money big changes were made at the end
of the day the bigger thing kind of
stayed the same
that's a some number of scenarios I
don't know what the percentage chances
of that but it's you know it exists it's
there in his pits
anyways the more the more the more
plausible scenarios sure now of course
as the as this as this as the situation
continues to develop this creates
opportunity for change right and so this
is one of the questions is agency who's
actually per to coming into the system
trying to move things around like the
Saudi Russian oil thing that was people
trying to actually take advantage of
chaos or take advantage of crisis and
say oh hey maybe I can shift this thing
a lot because leverage is there yeah so
one of the questions is gonna be what
else happens there what else happens
that's driven by people by agents
deliberately injecting more chaos into
the system because they want to shift
the system in their preferred direction
right now if they do that they might and
we may not notice it but there's also
circumstances where particular
injections create cascade effects there
there may there are a whole set of
scenarios where things actually spiral
out of control or the the the amount of
complexity is changing everyday to the
point where like we try to solve the
problem in our various solution actually
creates more problems over here you know
so in that case risk of information and
disinformation all having an effect here
is that's a big one that's a really big
one misinformation disinformation which
is sort of a primary weapon in the
modern era yeah and we're very
susceptible to it because we don't have
trustworthy institutions we've kind of
lost trust of our institutions and we
haven't build new ways to be good at
making sense in the modern information
environment so it's sort of like right
in the middle of a transition of that
capacity and it's very vulnerable yeah
and so you know they can world World War
two they have like the loose lips sink
ships this was something more like see
something say something or even better
tell the truth it's probably the most
important thing right now like right now
the moral lesson not to tell the truth
and so yeah I've actually talked through
a couple of folks about it so in a
context like this let's go the first
scenario is that we kind of muddle
through and we'll be able to know like
well we'll see if the medical systems
start popping and and there can that
that financial system starts to move out
it at our you know in the month two
months you know either settles down or
it doesn't and if it doesn't think we'll
just continue to be really really really
challenging
now generally speaking I can simplify
generally speaking outside of muddle
through you actually have two possible
major clusters of scenarios
one's really bad and one's actually
really good I think is opportunity and
the determinant of that is actually
something I think very powerful and very
fundamental and it's it's very simple
and the metaphor uses is the depression
and in Germany and the United States
okay sir so the Great Depression hits
financial crisis hits stock public
market explodes and actually happened in
both places happen all over the world
but it happened the US and Germany then
in the u.s. it was a big deal right the
financial system was blown up the
economic system was hammered people were
really seriously out of work and
impoverished people were starving
literally starving to death
my bad stuff was happened but at the
level of community it hung together and
got stronger neighbor helped neighbor
people pulled together they realized
that they had a common wheel they had a
common wealth that they all had
collective responsibility to maintain
and more or less on the United States
that fabric the foundational fabric of
civilization actually came together and
got stronger okay
people did not atomized and become
us-versus-them they became we and on the
basis of we economic and financial
questions can be solved rights are
really cool things that we use to solve
problems community is foundational all
right now switch over to Germany now
poor Germany had been dealt a bad hand
and wasn't one they got absolutely
hammered their old legacy Imperial
governor and the Kaiser had been booted
so they were sitting on top of the
Weimar Republic which didn't have a lot
of legitimate steam was actually run
through with all kinds of very
hyperbolic competing groups who are much
more interested in fighting each other
than trying to actually do the right
thing for the whole so their financial
system got torn through their economic
system got hammered but their community
fell apart
we became us versus them get one began
looking out for their own interests
withdrawing from the Commonwealth which
made the financial and economic
systems even more fragile which being
deposited a downward spiral and of
course he then had a transition into
Nazism right which is a very bad place
to be
and I'm not saying by the way so
Venezuela is a similar dynamic in
another direction right you either got
really serious hardcore bad
authoritarianism or really serious
hardcore bad chaos and then kind of one
threatens the other right the threat of
chaos the law student says well I'd
rather have a authoritarian the threat
of at or thora Tyrion can lead to chaos
it's either of those are sort of
equivalently bad places to be sure and
so in many ways like the balls in our
Court
as people as individuals at the end of
the days its if we are able to maintain
a community level feel we feel on the
ground yep is essential for seeing how
we are able to weather the storm and and
really what what direction we come out
of it at the end of the day that's right
that's right and this is so it's one of
these things where the die is not cast
right it's in our hands
I remember this great scene from the
movie Apollo 13 yeah where uh the guy
from Westworld Edie something he's the
guy who's like we're in the best in the
tie and in the background or the sort of
the the kind of the more bureaucratic
but the administrative heads at the guys
were at his bosses but aren't
responsible sitting in the back talking
and they're like all the big storms
coming and with all these things failing
and blabbity blah it's like yeah and
this is gonna be the greatest disaster
in NASA history he like tightens his tie
and turns and says gentlemen I think
this is gonna be our finest hour and
that's the difference right the
difference is he was committed he
was gonna make it work and in that
context crisis is an opportunity for
building entirely new good things and
there remember why not but back to the
beginning this crisis is not the problem
this crisis is a symptom of the fact
that we are addicts we are addicted to
extracting Clini tude in exchange for
fragility yep and the good news is you
can actually have both abundance and
resilience and those two are mutually
compatible there's a place to go which
is actually based upon very clearly
building more we unless us versus them
well you actually get to have abundance
Andrews
and you completely can deal with these
kinds of problems enduring and and the
we today we're talking about it's at the
community level but really we're also
talking we at the global level right one
of the one of the you know criticisms of
the way this crisis has been handled is
that the us used to be the leader in
terms of getting everybody to work
together a global on a global plane
unfortunately they have we have not been
the leader in this particular case and
you know it's it's a situation where
globally you know there could be a lot
more cooperation there could be a lot
more of how do we solve this together
and share information and share our
resources to get to a place where we're
all benefiting we're not there yet maybe
we'll get there I my hope is there but
the we part is really community and
global correct yeah absolutely but we
have to be very clear it can't be naive
and it's really crucial and by the way I
think I was just thinking this as you're
saying it that you're in the past I'm do
under the American hegemony like it's
quite quite clear after world war two
under the American hegemony we we led
and we led for two reasons we led
because in some sense we were the best
position to lead if anybody was gonna
lead was gonna be us and if we if we
didn't leaders can be hard for other
people to pull things off we also lived
because nobody else had in choice you
know what America decided to do
everybody else was more or less going to
have to play within that construct and
in many cases I think we tried to lead
with the with the real intent of for the
better for the benefit of all not in all
cases for sure but in many cases you
know I think that was the immune the
American Empire
unfortunately they decided to give the
imperial rob was in the in the larger
arc of history a relatively benevolent
Empire but that ain't there anymore and
we're now in a mode of a truly
multipolar world you know China can
definitely decide its own fate Europe
can decide its own thing
Russia is sophisticated at deciding
their own fate they can actually punch
above their grave and America can no
longer simply move left everybody has to
move left with us that's actually not
necessarily a bad thing because now it
means that if there is going to be
cooperative
it actually has to be cooperation people
actually have to choose to cooperate on
the basis of true community you know so
that's gonna be an interesting question
because no yeah we can't I can't help it
governments aren't good at that and the
kinds of people who tend to rise to the
top of large bureaucratic institutions
tend not to be the kinds of people who
are good at that they tend to be the
kinds of people who are good at making
sure they win fair they win us with us
them games we have some work to do there
right yeah quite rapidly by the way
agreed and so couple things you
mentioned right in your article that you
wrote yesterday we're moving towards
what you want to see as maybe what's
called a self-organizing collective
intelligence write a little bit about
that because what you're really saying
is that's the formula yeah if we are
able to put that in place in this weak
community over a period of time that
that helps us solve for a number of the
fragility you know system states that
were in currently today yeah absolutely
so there's there's there's really too
quickly just two dimensions to it it's
not that it's not actually that
complicated
so one dimension again is just this
basic notion of community is the notion
of people choosing to collaborate to
achieve greater than they could
individually and in support of something
that all of them consider to be mutually
valuable right that's we were familiar
with that thank God and it's just
getting better at that like actually
getting better at doing things like okay
where can I contribute my value best to
support the larger story and how do I
discern you know who are the people that
I should be supporting and listening to
all that kind of stuff like just getting
better at that but then the second is
the the world that we are in at the
technological level in particular
affords such a capacity to communicate
and to coordinate and to do together
across at a global scale there just
wasn't
present prior to now you know the the
good folks of the 50s and the 60s built
the world we live in using the tools of
radio television automobiles interstate
highways were like the big thing during
the Eisenhower administration and they
built that world we're still largely
using the institutional structures that
were built by and for that world okay it
is entirely possible like no no question
that as we begin to innovate new
structures of coordination that are
appropriate to capabilities of the
contemporary environment if those
structures for coordination will be
vastly more effective more capable more
capacitive less expensive will produce
less uncertainty and less extra nowadays
less blowback with unintended
consequences sure can be completely non
extractive and can actually be the kinds
of things that people enjoy
participating in they don't have to
actually sort of subordinate their
personal aspirations to kind of be a
good worker yep more to the point
they're the only things that can deal
with a pace and complexity of the
environment that we're in yeah so what's
that look like let me just give you like
a very simple example I'll do like a two
topologically ones already happening I
one is this global mass movement to be
able to find curate process and present
real-time accurate true information
about what's going on that people can
use yeah right and that's happening
right now and it's happening very well I
think it is the general under experience
that the internet when that is doing
just a flat-out better job than the
official channels at getting information
to people yeah right and I mean that by
the way it's really beautiful about is
they can be quite nuanced so if I just
need to know a few things I can get that
if I need to know very specific things
either local to me
or local to my area of expertise I get
that too that's a very fine-grain thing
that couldn't happen like when I'm
watching NBC everybody has to watch this
same show so there maybe even if they're
doing their best they're barely giving
me anything relevant to me and yeah and
frankly they're very rarely doing their
best these days okay so that's one
simple one sure and it's kind of wrote I
mean we've seen this happen you know
Craigslist replaced classifieds this is
that but just doing that in the domain
of real time information and and
building out by the way building our
content so right now we're seeing the
emergence of community groups and these
community groups all of them are kind of
trying to solve with basic same set of
problems you know how do we make sure
that everybody in the community has
enough food and water how do we make
sure we take care of the album how do we
take care of kids so that parents can
actually go do other stuff that the
community needs like if you've got a
single mom who's a nurse somebody in
your community is to go to her and say
we will take care of your kid cuz you're
taking care of this community right
you know that's happening Google
Spreadsheets on that there's handbooks
people are writing about the coronavirus
tech handbook as an example of a real
good basically where you can get all the
information pertinent for many different
places and figure out how to remember
that's not being produced by the CDC
that's being hacked together by just
people doing it and as better people
come online people are just handing it
off to him say can you do it all right
and it's building building building by
the way it's worse type of community
effort on very delicate areas right so
love that so let's take that now let's
do the next one the next one is like
okay what about hard stuff right I mean
don't we still need to have you know
NASA to go to the moon and I think we
may but it's not so long but there's -
unlike in the tech sector so one of the
biggest challenges that we have and by
maybe even fact these central challenges
is detection this thing has a powerful
characteristic of being undetectable or
asymptomatic for a long time so you've
got you know they walk among you there
are people your teen days yes there
there are people who don't have a clue
that they're sick yes walking around
creating the possibility of the people
getting sick yeah that's more or less
the whole problem and even if we were to
Institute a major quarantine if we can't
detect whether or not there are sick
people getting around if the sickness is
still spreading we don't know when to
stop
yeah we don't if we do stop we would
know if a second waves come through all
right so detection is a major problem
and there's a lot of Americans they're
spread out all over the place and our
current detection technology isn't up to
snuff it's too slow it's 70s technology
like they have to actually ship them
back to a big lab and batiks process I
mean all that crap all right
there's already exists a technology that
can solve the problem it's called gene
radar and fortunately that information
processing thing brought this to my
attention now a bunch of smart people
know this is the case they talked to the
people who were there checked it they
said oh wow this thing was built to deal
with the Zika virus it can totally be
repurposed to the coronavirus already
has been it's already an FDA fast track
trials to solve the problem as we can
yes and it could be scaled yeah to be
able to get a device in the hands of
every hospital in the country and could
do five million tests a day okay now
here's the thing we could do that
through a couple different paths one
path might be the White House White
House might say that's part of the
solution go make it happen old-fashioned
government and that'd be great
right great solution another path might
be more decentralized right the Mormon
Church these guys did worked wonders
during Katrina
there are Mormons everywhere they have a
lot of resources and all of them already
have food and water taken care of and if
I could they have a unusually like
larger than general level of care for
community
yeah well the Mormon Church could become
as effective at dealing with this virus
as the Debbie Joe and the CDC as
combined because the leverage of
technology can enable that to happen
right it wouldn't actually with for 250
million dollars and with people being
able to pull together like a whole
community people working together again
boom could be done and in fact you could
do a frickin Kickstarter
you could get people signed up all over
the country to say I will take one when
it's ready and I will make sure that
we're ready to start doing testing pull
together 250 million dollars get the
supply chain managed appropriately we
could do a full Apollo 13 project but at
the community level and any one of these
three paths could be done right now we
have the capacity to do it the hard
science in R&D has been done but we had
to fight it right it's an information
processing and one it's important in the
context of where we are right now but -
I think it's also very important to
grasp that this is generally the case
we've got a lot of problems we have to
solve as a civilization most of the
solutions we already have it's not
really about inventing new things in
some cases there will be but in most
cases it's actually finding the people
who actually been doing incredible work
for decades that haven't been perceived
and upregulated by our current fragile
institutions yeah and then resourcing
them in a context that actually has the
leverage of communitas right that is
almost certainly the solution that moves
us through this thing to the other side
fantastic all right man thank you
you got it that was fun appreciate it
yeah I really probably and I think this
is gonna be very helpful for people
understand you know the virus is step
one it's what everybody's focused on but
we're really here talking about the
second order third order items that are
really you know cascade effects of the
virus yeah you know I just you just
reminded me I forgot so so we did that
whole loop and I just want to loop back
to this edition of global because I
think it's very very important for
everyone to get into their consciousness
that nation-states are fake right
they're artificial these are the only
thing that is real okay and if we just
get that in our head and we take full
responsibility as individuals for the
well-being of our fellows for the common
what is it called the brotherhood of man
then we're good to go that we can deal
with it um all right that's all brother
Thank You Man appreciate it love ya see
you soon take care